<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Johan Van den Rym</title>
    <description>Thought about code and design.</description>    
    <link></link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>The meat of the burger icon</title>
        <description>&lt;h2&gt;Why hamburger icons?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The viewport on mobile devices especially smart phones in portrait mode needs carefully managing of the screen real estate. Navigation lists can be too wide to fit in the horizontal available space of the viewport. Add other elements like logo and search form and the available space is little on smaller viewport sizes like tablets and mobile phones. The hamburger UI design pattern tries to solve that. The navigation that would not fit otherwise is set to a hidden state. The hamburger icon controls the visible state of the navigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The burger icon design pattern was already used long before mobile and responsive got into the picture. Xerox Star (1970s) used it for contextual menus already then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The use of the burger icon (responsive menu) as a design pattern emerged from mobile and found its way to the desktop as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;lazy&quot; data-src=&quot;/assets/images/burger_desktop.jpg&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Example of burger icon on desktop&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Navigation and UI&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been studies that question the efficiency of the burger icon as a design pattern. It would be not significant enough to associate it with navigational elements. A &lt;a href=&quot;http://exisweb.net/menu-eats-hamburger&quot;&gt;usability study&lt;/a&gt; was conducted to find out how people would react to the burger icon. A textual label &#39;MENU&#39; would aid to clarify the meaning of the burger icon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case &lt;a href=&quot;http://thenextweb.com/dd/2014/04/08/ux-designers-side-drawer-navigation-costing-half-user-engagement/&quot;&gt;hiding navigation&lt;/a&gt; behind a burger icon could prove detrimental to the end-user&#39;s perception of what the site or app has to offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The icon appears both left and right on the top of the viewport. What is better left or right? It depends on the design and has not been standardized. It has little of influence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Providing a animated current state change proves very effective. As showcased here by using &lt;a href=&quot;http://sarasoueidan.com/blog/navicon-transformicons/&quot;&gt;CSS 3 transformations&lt;/a&gt; that indicate the state change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;inline-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;lazy&quot; data-src=&quot;/assets/images/modal.jpg&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Example of a modal-like pattern&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class=&quot;inline-image&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;lazy&quot; data-src=&quot;/assets/images/modal_active.jpg&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Example of a modal-like  pattern (active state)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Rethinking the design pattern is always possible in the near future. Not every project is put under the scrutiny of A/B testing. Often existing patterns are applied without evaluating first if it is the right design decision.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>/2014/10/10/the-beefy-icon/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2014/10/10/the-beefy-icon/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Andy budd about user experience</title>
        <description>&lt;h2&gt;Who is Andy Budd?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andy Budd is design and user experience lead at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.clearleft.com/&quot;&gt;Clearleft&lt;/a&gt; and author of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://andybudd.com/&quot;&gt;Blogography&lt;/a&gt; weblog. This interview I conducted for Fadtastic back in 2006. Almost a decade ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Is the profession of web designer moving more towards interaction design that is graphic design + information design + human-computer interaction?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andy: Most definitely. As the industry matures, website owners and users want more than just a pretty interface. Website owners want to differentiate their products and services from their competition by providing their customers with a better experience. Users want something that solves real problems in an enjoyable and easy to use way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The concept of user experience may be relatively new on the web, but we’ve seen this cycle many times before. Take consumer electronics. Early products are usually expensive and feature-poor. As the industry grows, the technology is the first thing to get refined and so companies start competing on looks instead of features. Once product lines start to become both fashionable and technically identical, the next logical step is to make them easier and more pleasurable to use.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Does user experience stand usually for user-centric design or is it more?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andy: User experience design is a difficult term to define as it actually relates to a whole series of disciplines, of which user-centered design is just one. With user-centered design you typically focus on the functional needs of the user to make a product or service that fits in with their life. User experience design pushes this concept slightly further, by not only creating something that is easy to use, but creating something that is actually a pleasure to use.
How can we provide quality of a user experience?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The best way to ensure a good experience is to research user needs; bring your creative problem solving skills to bare in order to design a solution; test that solution on real users, and then iterate based on their feedback. Good user experience design is an ongoing process rather than a one off commodity.
Is the access to information the key factor in interaction design?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andy: Easy access to information is obviously a key factor in web usability which forms a huge part of interaction design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Feedback of users is invaluable but how do you evaluate this?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andy: Very carefully. Users often try to be helpful and offer suggestions about why they thought a particular interaction was problematic or how it could be improved. However it turns out that people actually aren’t very good at evaluating their own actions and their reasoning can often be wildly off. As such it is much better to evaluate what users do rather than what they say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;A last question: do you have an example of a website(-s) that provides a great user experience?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andy: User experience is very personal, so what may provide a great experience for one set of users may provide a confusing experience to another group. Take Flickr. I personally love the user experience of this site–despite a few usability issues–but other people can find it confusing. Conversely there are millions of teenagers who think MySpace is the best thing in the world, despite the fact that it looks like the back end of a bus and is about as usable as a chocolate teapot.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2006 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>/2006/06/06/interview-with-andy-budd/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2006/06/06/interview-with-andy-budd/</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>